We are in northern India, in Jharkhand.
One of the poorest regions in the country.
Deep in the crevices of this cliff,
20 or so men and women
are rummaging through the dirt.
They are mining for mica.
There are thousands of mines like this
spread across the Jharkhand region.
They are not run by big corporations.
Each person collects these stones
for themselves.
I earn between 100 and 200 rupees,
depending on the market price.
I have to sell an entire basket
full like this one here.
Do you know what mica is?
No, I don't.
-Do you know what it is used in?
-No.
-You don't know what it's used for?
-No, I don't.
For just over a dollar,
these women are working eight-hour days
under a blazing sun.
What more can I do? I'm poor.
I would rather work in the mines
than die of starvation.
It's not just adults
working in these mines.
Further down the valley,
we spot a group of children.
Kids aged between six and nine,
working in heat that can reach
temperatures of 116 degrees Fahrenheit.
My name is Gagan Kugar,
I'm eight years old.
We come together every Sunday.
What do you do on the other days?
I go to school to study.
What time do you get to the mine?
6:00 am.
Do you like doing it?
No, but I can buy school supplies
like books and pens to write with.
Do you buy anything else?
Soap and food too.
This desert landscape
hosts hills that are full of this mineral.
India is the largest producer
of these shiny strips,
found by simply reaching down
and collecting them from the ground.
This raw material
is little known to the public,
but is in fact integral
for a multitude of products
that we use in our everyday lives.
It can be found in car paint,
as an isolating material
for electronic parts,
and even as an ingredient
in the cosmetics industry.
When crushed into a powder, mica is found
in almost every beauty product.
Mica.
To find out more
about the product's importance
in the beauty industry,
we head to the Carrousel du Louvre
at the Makeup in Paris Trade Fair,
destined for cosmetic professionals
and experts in this raw material.
There aren't any stands for Chanel,
Dior, or L'Oréal here,
as most big brands like these
don't make their own products.
Instead, outsourcing to manufacturers
who are mostly in Italy.
Natural mica is an essential ingredient
in makeup such as mascara,
blush, lipstick, and foundation.
With this, we're just physically pressing
organic pigments into mica.
The way most companies formulate,
they typically use mica as the base for,
let's say, a pressed powder.
Mica gives the product a shiny quality.
With its large particles,
you can get a more prominent glow.
However, when mica is smaller,
it can be used as a base for the product.
i.e. The product loses its clarity
which in turn intensifies the color.
When it's applied,
the color comes out a lot brighter.
Look at this shine,
you can see the glitter in it.
Basically, there's mica everywhere.
Yes, you find it in shampoo,
you find it in toothpaste,
everywhere you have this pearly effect,
you have mica products.
Manufacturers are well-versed
in their recipes and processes,
but do they know
where their raw materials are sourced?
Hello, I am Brando Baranzelli.
They're aware of the child labor issues
and claim
that they are very concerned about it.
We have suppliers
that certify their products' origin.
It's up to them to take every step
of the process into account.
We trust our suppliers
and what they tell us.
We also use regulatory organizations
that certify our suppliers
don't use child labor.
We only use mica
for which we know the source,
and if the supplier is part of an official
list of multinational companies,
because these companies
are well aware of this problem
and are constantly tackling it.
They draw up lists of suppliers
that are socially responsible
and respect the correct ethical standards.
However, what is the real story
behind these claims?
Mica can be found all over the world.
The major producers
are the US, South Korea,
Brazil, Canada, China,
and of course, India.
According to the official organisation
Eurostat,
India represents 30%
of all mica imported into Europe.
Officially, mica produced in India
comes from Rajasthan.
However, in reality,
most of the deposits are found
in the states of Jharkhand and Bihar,
a region where mica mining
happens illegally and in secret.
Almost 90% of mica.
Can we really be sure
of the conditions
in which this essential mineral
for our skin is extracted?
We are back in Jharkhand.
These wild valleys,
which spread for miles,
were declared a natural reserve
by the state in the 1990s.
In order to protect them,
the authorities banned all mica mining.
However, this drone footage shows
that there are huge numbers of mines here.
These surface craters
testify to the sheer amount of mining
that's been carried out by villagers,
even in areas
that are very difficult to access.
Some miners are using dynamite
to open up the mountains,
while others use more rudimentary methods.
In order to understand why this mining
has taken place for over 40 years,
despite the bans in place,
we decided to get in touch
with the miners.
It was hard to spot them in the field.
After two days of searching,
we met a family.
Anil is 25 years old.
Every day, he comes here to mine mica
with his wife and children.
Mica is the only option for us.
We have all come here to work
and earn around 300 to 400 rupees
so we can buy rice and feed ourselves.
I want them to study,
to do something with their lives.
I want them to have a good job.
Anil wasn't always a miner.
Just two years ago,
he was working as a farmer.
He lives in this village,
located at the foot of the mines,
with a population of around 60 people.
There is no running water or electricity
despite the brand-new poles.
The family's livelihood
used to be farming.
However, due to drought
and climate change,
most of the land is now barren.
This is my land, here, all of this.
Can you still farm on this land?
No, of course not.
If there is no rain then nothing can grow.
It's bone dry.
The extraction of mica
is now an essential source of revenue
for more than 90%
of Jharkhand's population.
Miners are willing to take huge risks
to get their hands on it.
Over-mined on the surface,
they have to go deeper and deeper
in order to find this precious mineral.
The sound of mining work
near a well caught our attention.
[Foreign spoken audio]
Don't worry, we're not police.
Okay, no problem.
-What is your name?
-Karan Singh.
How do you deal with working down there?
When you're hungry,
you're not afraid to go down.
Yes, it's dangerous work,
but what else can you do?
I need to eat,
I don't really have a choice.
I haven't studied a lot
and I don't get any help
from the government.
Karan is 35 years old
and has two children.
He allows us to follow him
into the tunnel he has built.
Every month,
around 12 miners die in the region
because of these dangerous
underground quarries.
Almost 50 feet underground,
their supply is running low.
It's around 113 degrees,
and there's nothing in place
to hold up the structure.
It could collapse at any moment.
Karan and his friend Ravi
spend eight hours a day
in the darkness here.
This ordeal brings them
around 300 rupees a day.
The equivalent of 2.75 dollars.
I've worked here for four months.
We've had a lot of people
working here in the past.
Our ancestors worked here
40 to 50 years ago.
Are you aware that people die
due to these mines collapsing?
I am scared for my life
like anyone would be,
but what else can I do?
There aren't too many accidents here.
If God so chooses, it will happen,
but for now,
there haven't been any disasters here.
Mica can be found on the surface
but higher quantities
can be found underground.
Here, for example, there are large stones,
whereas up here there isn't any mica,
so we haven't touched it.
There's a lot over there
so we head that way.
It's good quality here too.
Does it not worry you
that what you're doing is illegal?
The police came around four
or five months ago.
They said that it's illegal
and that we have to stop.
They even tried to scare us sometimes,
but how are we going to feed ourselves
if we don't come here?
They said they'll do everything
in their power to arrest us
and take us to the station.
They've arrested us at times
but then let us go afterward
because they know we're poor.
Sometimes they take a bit of money
from us, 1,000 rupees max.
The mountain however is less forgiving.
Karan plays down the danger,
but people have died in his own village.
These two miners live in Tisri,
a town with a population of around 4,000
that is surrounded by mining deposits.
Mining is the main source of income here.
Three years ago, disaster hit.
This woman lost her husband to the mines.
She has four children.
Sit down and eat.
Like most of the Jharkhand villagers,
she cannot read or write.
My name is Anita Devi.
I don't know how old I am,
my parents don't remember.
Can you tell us about your husband?
My husband left to work in the mines,
he went deep into the ground
and was buried alive after a landslide.
-Did others die?
-Yes, three others.
Since her husband died,
Anita is the only provider for her family.
Every day, she walks over a mile
under the hot sun on rocky paths
before reaching the summit
of this mountain.
When they aren't at school,
her children come with her to work.
The youngest is just four years old.
The children help me
to collect the small rocks.
We crush and collect the rock debris
that is on the surface.
Therefore, I earn less.
Mommy something has got into my foot.
Show me, show me.
Show me, otherwise, I'll get annoyed!
This is my daily ordeal,
working in the heat.
I can deal with hunger
but not my children.
I won't let them starve.
I have to work
as I don't have any land to farm.
After three hours,
Anita and her children
have collected enough
to feed themselves for a day.
It's a poor man's work,
but many big businesses rely on it.
Back with Karan and Ravi.
We're trying to understand
where their mica goes once it's sold.
Is it destined for the European market?
Where does the mica go
once you have collected it?
To the city of Giridih.
Who do you give it to?
Someone who comes to get it in Thana,
around four miles from the main road.
Are these people wholesalers over there?
Yes, the wholesalers come there to buy it.
Does it go to Giridih only after that?
Yes, they transport it there
because they have a license.
What sort of license?
You didn't know it was illegal?
Yes, you need a license
to be able to sell it.
Can we go and meet them?
Sure, if you go there
they'll explain everything,
You will see outside there
are big factories
next to the police station,
it's written in big letters.
We realized that despite this product
being illegally sourced,
it can be easily exchanged on the market
through several intermediaries.
At the end of each day,
the villagers take what they've collected
towards the valley to collection points
where the minerals are sold by weight.
Put it on here.
These small retailers
supply the production line
and sell mica to the local wholesalers.
The local residents direct me
to the wholesalers
that will eventually buy their product.
We head to the center of town
to meet them.
There were more than a dozen of them,
as mica production
is the town's only industry.
At first, they refused to be filmed.
Eventually, one of the wholesalers
agreed to respond
to our questions off-camera.
We filmed the following scenes
with a hidden camera.
Where does the mica come from?
The mica comes from the mines.
Is it the small retailers
that bring it to you?
Yes.
The wholesaler admits that the mica
is sourced from illegal mines.
However, as soon as we suggest
that it comes from child labor,
he shuts down.
We'd like to ask you
about children working in the mine.
Children don't work in the mica mines.
It's false information.
The children bring food to their parents
when they are working,
and the media takes photos of it.
-Therefore, children don't work there?
-No.
Do you export too?
No, we sell to the exporters.
It goes to Mumbai, China, Germany…
Who buys it in Germany?
Merck.
One of the main buyers of the mica
that's produced in the region is,
according to this man,
the German group Merck.
Merck is one of the largest corporations
in Germany.
Founded in 1668,
this multinational earns
over 16 billion dollars
in the chemical, cosmetics,
and pharmaceutical industries.
Merck has the oldest chemical
and pharmaceutical company,
bundles 350 years of expertise
from healthcare, life science,
and performance materials,
and translates it
into cosmetic ingredient development.
We call this translational cosmetics.
The European leader
in supplying raw materials
to the cosmetics industry.
Subsidiaries such as the Colorona
and Timiron Group
are the main mica pigment suppliers
to big brands
such as L'Oréal, Chanel, and Girling.
This is the Merck way
to innovate in beauty.
At this beauty trade fair,
we approach the representatives
of the German company
to question them on their supply chain.
It's a sensitive subject,
so we chose not to warn them
that we were coming.
Hello, nice to meet you,
I'm Brando, Special Report.
We're making a film
about the cosmetics market and mica,
and we're visiting different stands
to talk to different producers.
Will you be able to answer
some of our questions?
-No one from communications is here.
-Sorry?
We don't have anyone from communications,
did you schedule this interview?
-No.
-They're in Germany and also on vacation.
You should have made
an appointment beforehand.
However, we haven't made an appointment
with the other stands.
We just asked people a few questions
and they answered them.
Well, we don't work like that.
The stand manager
suggests we write an email
to her colleagues in Germany.
We did this the next day.
The company declined our offer
of an interview without giving any reason.
"Unfortunately,
I cannot offer you an appointment"
"for a personal interview."
Whilst waiting, they suggested we read
their corporate responsibility information
accessible on their website.
It claims a zero-tolerance policy
for child labor.
"We have completely reorganized
our supply chain"
"and now source the raw material
exclusively from qualified mines."
"The control of relevant documentation,
worker's ages, working hours and wages,"
"as well as compliance with environmental,
safety, and health standards."
"By means of audits, we strictly monitor
the compliant behavior of our partners,"
"who've agreed to adhere to the principles
of our Human Rights Charter"
"as well as the requirements
of our Responsible Sourcing Principles."
To confirm these statements,
we headed back to India,
to Koderma, a city in northern Jharkhand.
This town, with a population of 24,000,
is the hub of the mica industry,
containing the majority
of the export businesses
and treatment facilities.
Hello? Who is it?
Shaitan is 25 years old
and he's one of the exporters in town.
When I introduce myself as a journalist,
he agrees to show me his warehouses
and respond to questions
about child labor.
Hassan, go and get some material.
He has to have the material ready here
next to the machine.
His business has around 50 employees.
The process involves
screening the raw materials.
They are placed in the screener,
where all the sand particles
and impurities are removed.
The resulting material
will be clean and free of sand.
Sorted, ground, and filtered,
the crystals
are then refined one final time
before becoming the final product.
These are impurity-free mica flakes.
It is widely used in pigments
and cosmetic industries.
Impurity-free mica flakes.
These precious mica flakes are wrapped
and then exported to Europe,
and sold at around 550 dollars per ton.
Listening to the young entrepreneur,
there's a good reason
his mica isn't sourced
from mines that use child labor.
It comes from Rajasthan,
where extraction is legal
and controlled by the authorities.
This is a lorry from Rajasthan
that comes from the legal mica mines
and unloads at our factory.
There, all the mica mines
are legally run by their owners.
According to NGOs, three-quarters
of the country's mica deposits
aren't situated in Rajasthan,
but rather around Koderma in Jharkhand.
When working on the Merck investigation,
we found a database
that records mica exports
from the port in Kolkata.
We saw that Merck gets several containers
a week delivered to Germany
and is supplied
by two exporters based in Koderma.
Ramdew Modi
and Pachisia and Company.
Both are businesses that we know well.
When we were conducting
our investigation in the villages,
the wholesaler confirmed
that these businesses
work with illegal mines.
Do you export too?
No, we sell to the exporters.
-To Ramdew Modi too?
-Yes, exactly.
Pachisia too?
Pachisia… Yes.
I supply them too,
they are in charge of exporting it.
We managed to find these two suppliers
to Merck on the outskirts of Koderma.
They're located right next to one another.
We pay them a visit
with our hidden cameras.
As soon as we arrive at Pachisia,
all the workers scurry away
in a matter of seconds.
Only one man welcomes us.
A man who seems to be the boss.
-Brando?
-Yes.
Posing as a potential buyer,
I try to find out more
about his suppliers and clients,
but the man quickly becomes suspicious.
Actually, at the moment,
I'm very sorry that I am unable
to discuss any business topics
without my father's permission
because he is the senior person.
-Your father?
-Yes.
We hit a brick wall.
After, we head to Ramdew Modi.
We're welcomed by the foremen,
and the boss says over the phone
that he can't see us.
Disappointed, we are getting ready
to leave when we spot another factory
just 100 feet away from the first two.
This time, the boss is there
and he welcomes us with open arms.
He knows his neighbors well
and works with them often.
Still posing as a potential buyer,
I ask him about Ramdew Modi and Pachisia.
They've been doing that for a long time,
their mica basically goes to Merck.
Merck in Germany.
The man is happy to chat
and reveals the secrets
about trade with foreign countries.
-Are they allowed to export?
-Yes, they've got an export license.
They don't have any mining operations,
but they manage
to get the documents anyway.
Their merchandise comes from here.
It's not legal at all.
You can get licenses
from Rajasthan or Belwahra
because there is mica there.
To appear above board,
the exporters use licenses from there.
While their mica
comes from illegal mines in Jharkhand,
the trick for exporters
is to buy a license from Rajasthan,
to make their businesses legitimate,
and to export their products
with the correct paperwork.
The man then introduces us
to his colleague.
He informs us that it is also possible
for import businesses
to get a certificate of ethical conduct
regarding child labor.
All you have to do is pay.
If the buyer wants a certificate,
how can you do this?
You can get one with the business's name.
We find the paper,
we can do everything without any problems.
Therefore, it's feasible?
Yes, we take care of everything.
However, if you don't get these papers,
it will cost you a lot.
The administrative part is expensive.
How much?
Two or 2.5 rupees per kilo.
No matter where the mica is from,
it's easy to get papers that prove
it hasn't been produced by child labor.
Here is what the certificates look like.
This particular copy
comes from an Indian company
that provides international certification.
It ensures that the mica
has never been touched by a child's hands.
According to this Indian exporter,
these papers are a mandatory requirement
for international groups like Merck.
There's a phrase we use here:
"Does that mean that people
who don't own cows can't drink milk?"
In the same way,
if you aren't above board,
is it therefore impossible
to have the right paperwork?
That's how the world works.
Of course, large corporations like Merck
conduct their own inspections.
However, according to this boss,
exporters also have tricks
to get around this.
When Merck inspectors come,
for example when Mr. X came here,
he asked me to bring him
to the mines for a visit.
Were there children working in the mines?
Yes, there are children
working in the mines too
but on the day of the inspection,
there wasn't a child in sight.
No women or children.
How can we be sure
that the mica
imported by this German group
has never passed through a child's hands?
Upon my return to Paris,
I wanted to confront the Merck Group
with my investigation.
I sent an email
to the communications department
recounting the discoveries
I had made in India
during our investigation in Koderma.
We spoke with some of their partners
who told us that both Ramdew and Pachisia,
like all other exporters,
provide themselves
with mica collectors in Jharkhand,
whose mica comes from illegal mines
involving child labor.
In their response, the business sent us
their corporate responsibility information
again, assuring us,
"Based on our available information,"
"your statement that our suppliers
would source third-party mica"
"from illegal mines
involving child labor is incorrect."
Continuing our research,
we found a Paris-based association,
the Responsible Mica Initiative.
An organization
that seeks to eradicate child labor
in the Indian mica mines.
It states that it lobbies
the Indian authorities
and carries out social action
in nearly 80 villages across Jharkhand.
Among the 50 or so sponsors
are Merck, L'Oréal, Chanel,
and Yves Rocher.
The manager for France
has agreed to meet with us.
-Hello, nice to meet you.
-Nice to meet you.
At their offices,
we show her images
that we filmed in the mines in India.
It's unbearable to watch this,
that's why we need to act and act now.
This is why our organization was founded
and why we have fixed
extremely ambitious objectives,
aiming to eradicate child labor by 2022.
Fanny Freeman is aware
that child labor is still an issue,
but assured us
that it's out of the question
for brands to leave the region.
If these businesses
decided to stop buying mica from India,
in the end,
it's the families that would suffer
from losing their own income,
so this is why I say it is brave to stay,
to know there is a problem,
but to say to ourselves: "We're staying,"
"we're aware and we're doing everything
in our power to solve it".
Mica is their only source of revenue.
If all of the businesses left India
and sourced elsewhere,
it would have disastrous social
and economic consequences.
Towards the end of our investigation,
we made one last discovery.
We're back in the mining region of Tisri.
Over recent years
of excessive exploitation,
mining has had an impact
on the health of the population.
The village hospital
has a room dedicated to people
suffering from tuberculosis.
Bishupal is waiting for his appointment.
He has spent ten years
working in the mica mines.
Bishupal, you can go in.
For the past month, he's been suffering
with respiratory problems.
-What is the problem?
-I have a cough.
-For how long?
-A month.
Come here.
The doctor in this makeshift hospital
sees a hundred or so patients a day.
Try to cough. Cough, cough, cough…
Around 60% of them
are suffering from coughs.
Do these tests and begin treatment.
Return with the test results,
and I'll prescribe other medication,
depending on the results.
Many people who work in these mining
areas are exposed to dust particles,
which can lead
to problems like tuberculosis,
especially when the exposure is prolonged.
There's a chance that more than 80
to 90% of the workers
may face health issues due to the dust.
The complications can affect
not only those working in the mines
but also anyone
living in this environment,
as they too may be affected
by the same problems.
Take one tablet
every evening after dinner.
Do these non-regulated mines
risk having an impact
on the health of an entire generation?
We can't really say, but these hospitals
located in mining regions
see a higher rate of pulmonary illnesses
than anywhere else in India.
However, local residents
aren't aware of this,
and children are particularly at risk.
An association from Koderma is campaigning
to alert the miners in the villages.
We talk with the villagers,
advising them not to work in the mines
because it has a very bad impact
on their health.
We also encourage them
to send their children to school,
as education is very important.
We primarily raise awareness
about the health hazards
of working in mica mines.
Raul is 24 years old
and comes daily to the mines
accompanied by these local campaigners.
He goes to families
one by one to warn them.
-Do you come and help sometimes?
-Yes.
-Do you like going to school?
Today, the group is going to focus
on the family's mother.
They're asking her to stop her activity
and listen to their recommendations.
After a short negotiation,
she agrees to take them to her home.
On their way there,
the group attempts to build
a friendly rapport with the miners.
Panchia Devi lives here
with her four children.
Her husband lives in Delhi.
She has to take care of them on her own.
Are you aware of the problems that you
and your children
are facing when you go into the mines?
No, I've been going since I was little,
and my daughter
only helps from time to time.
What you need to know
is that when you are sorting the mica,
dust is released.
As a result,
children risk catching tuberculosis
and will also develop a cough.
People working in the mines
or those who sort the mica
are often diagnosed with tuberculosis.
The dust enters the airways
and settles in the lungs.
which prevents them
from functioning properly.
When these airways are blocked,
it's difficult to breathe.
The activist then makes
his strongest possible argument
with the mother.
Imagine if the authorities decided
to stop them mining for good,
given that it's illegal.
What would you do
if you no longer had work?
I believe in God, He will help us.
We don't have a choice here,
there's nothing else to do.
The residents of Jharkhand
are trapped in a vicious cycle.
They must choose between their health
or their survival.
According to the NGO,
the only possible solution
would be an aid plan for the development
of the region in order to create jobs.
However, the local residents
are still waiting for this.
How long will they have to wait?